A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 2014-2017
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Office of the Secretary of Education, 2014-2017
The Library of Virginia
52181
2.45 cu. ft. (7 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. If redaction was not an option, the entire document was sealed, but not removed from the collection. Sealed information may include, but is not limited to: medical information, social security numbers, and attorney-client privileged information.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Secretary of Education, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219. Accession 44681 transferred and accessioned on 12 January 2010.
Historical/Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariats positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
The Secretary of Education assists the Governor in the development and implementation of the state's education policy. The secretary provides guidance to 16 colleges and universities, the Virginia Community College System, five higher education and research centers, the Department of Education, the state-supported museums, and other agencies in the Education Secretariat. All secretaries are appointed by the governor and serve at his will.
During the Administration of Governor Terry McAuliffe (2014-2018) the Secretary of Education directed policy for education programs that involve multiple agencies including: Department of Education, Library of Virginia, Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Science Museum of Virginia and Virginia Commission for the Arts. While Virginia's Colleges and Universities are semi-autonomous, the Secretary of Education also plays a role in directing state policy for: Virginia Community Colleges, Christopher Newport University, George Mason University, James Madison University, Longwood University, Mary Washington University, Norfolk State University, Old Dominion University, Radford University, Richard Bland College, University of Virginia, Virginia Commonwealth University, Virginia Military Institute, Virginia State University, Virginia Tech, College of William and Mary, Roanoke Higher Education Center, Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center, and State Council of Higher Education.
Some of Governor McAuliffe's education initiatives were: early childhood initiatives, high school reform initiatives, Standards of Learning (SOL) Innovation, Sexual Assault Task Force, the conclusion, the termination of Governor McDonnell's Opportunity Educational Institute, and workforce development.
On 4 January 2014, Governor-elect McAuliffe named Anne Holton as Secretary of Education. After graduating with a B.A. from Princeton and a Harvard law degree, Holton worked as a legal aid lawyer serving low-income families. She served as a juvenile and domestic relations district court judge from 1998 until 2005. While serving as First Lady from 2006-2010 (married to Governor Tim Kaine), Holton devoted attention to children in the state's foster care system, working with the Virginia Community Colleges System as director of the Great Expectations program, which helps foster youths further their studies. Holton became the first First Lady to then go on to serve in a gubernatorial cabinet position. Jennie Moline O'Holleran, then Director of Virginia Relations at the George Washington University, and Dietra Trent, then Deputy State Director in Senator Mark Warner's Office were appointed as the two original Deputy Secretaries of Education in McAuliffe's Secretariat. Deputy Secretary O'Holleran served in this capacity until 2015 when she went on to serve as Senior Policy Advisory and then Policy Director in McAuliffe's administration.
Secretary Holton stepped down in July of 2016 to focus on her husband Tim Kaines campaign as Vice President for Hillary Rodham Clintons presidential bid. Governor McAuliffe appointed then Deputy Secretary Dr. Dietra Trent to the Secretary role. She previously served as Deputy Secretary of Education in Governor Tim Kaines administration, and as Director of Constituent Services and Director of the Council on Human Rights under Governor Mark Warner.
Scope and Content
The Records of the Virginia Secretary of Education are housed in seven (7) boxes. The collection is arranged into four (4) series. Series have been designated for: I. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2014-2017; II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Secretariat, 2014-2017; III. Special Projects and Studies: Deputy Secretariat, 2014-2017; IV. Special Projects and Studies: Secretariat, 2014-2017. These records include agendas, articles, briefings, correspondence, e-mails, grants, handouts, legislation, lists, memorandums, minutes, notes, presentations, press releases, reports, speeches, studies, surveys and files by subject and/or sender. These records document the work of the Secretary of Education under Governor Terry McAuliffe. The most significant and voluminous material documents the development and implementation of the various educational initiatives of the McAuliffe Administration including: P-16 Council, Sexual Assault Task Force, Workforce Development, Standards of Learning Innovation/Reform Committee, and Teacher Quality as well as correspondence from constituents and other officials. The bulk of the records document activity from 2014 through 2016, when the Secretary of Education was Anne Holton and Jennie Moline O'Holleran and Dr. Dietra Trent the Deputy Secretaries.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2014-2017
II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Secretariat, 2014-2017
III. Special Projects and Studies: Deputy Secretariat, 2014-2017
IV. Special Projects and Studies: Secretariat, 2014-2017
Related Material
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Education, 2006-2014(bulk 2009-2013).
The Governor Terry McAuliffe Administration Web Archive Collection, 2014-2018.
Contents List
- I. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2014-2017., Extent: .35 cubic feet (1 box). (Box 1)
  - Bryant and Straton College, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commission for the Arts, 2014-2017. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - George Mason University (GMU), 2014. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Library of Virginia, 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Norfolk State University (NSU), 2014-2016. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Opportunity Educational Institute, (1 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Opportunity Educational Institute, (2 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Opportunity Educational Institute, (3 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - (Director of) Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Intermont College (VIC). (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - University of Virginia (UVA), 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2014-2016. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Military Institute (VMI), 2014. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts (VMFA), 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Tech, 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- II. Correspondence and Subject Files: Secretariat, 2014-2017., Extent: 1.0 cubic feet (3 boxes). (Box 1-3)
  - Attorney General, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board Appointments, 2015-2016. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Budget, 2015-2016. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014-2016 (1 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014-2016 (2 of 4). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014-2016 (3 of 4). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014-2016 (4 of 4). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Communities in School, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dietra Trent, 2016-2017. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Early Childhood Foundation, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Elementary and Secondary Education Act, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Higher Education Access and Completion, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - House of Delegates, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC), 2015. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Literary Fund, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Nutrition, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Office of the Inspector General(OSIG), 2015. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Priorities, 2014-2015. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Recommendations, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Senate, 2014-2015. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Strategic Planning, 2014-2015. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Teacher Preparation, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Thank Yous/Congratulations, 2014-2016 (1 of 2). (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Thank Yous/Congratulations, 2014-2016 (2 of 2). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - University of Virginia - Office of Civil Rights (UVA-OCR), 2015. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Education Association (VEA), 2014-2015. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Voices for Virginia's Children, 2014. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- III. Special Projects and Studies: Deputy Secretariat, 2014-2017., Extent: 1.05 cubic feet (3 boxes). (Box 3-5;)
  - Accountability Committee, 2015. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Career and Technology Education (CTE), 2014. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Catholic Diocese of Richmond, 2014. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cisco Academy. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014 (1 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014 (2 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 2014 (3 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Constituent Correspondence-VIP, 2014 (1 of 2). (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Constituent Correspondence-VIP, 2014 (2 of 2). (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - E-Rate/Broadband, 2014. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Early Childhood Foundation, 2015. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Educate Every Child (E3), 2014. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Education Technology, 2015 (1 of 2). (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Education Technology, 2015 (2 of 2). (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Evaluations, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Excel to Excellence. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fairfax County Public Schools, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Governor Schools, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Initiatives, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - National Governors' Association (NGA) Governors' Education Policy Advisors (GEPA) Conference, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Opportunity Educational Institute, 2014 (1 of 2). (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Opportunity Educational Institute, 2014 (2 of 2). (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Parents as Teachers. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 2014-2015. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Proposals, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Proposals, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pulaski County Public Schools, 2015. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Roanoke City Public Schools, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL) Innovation Committee, 2014 (1 of 3). (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL) Innovation Committee, 2014 (2 of 3). (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL) Innovation Committee, 2014 (3 of 3). (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL) Reform, 2014 (1 of 2). (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL) Reform, 2014 (2 of 2). (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Teach for America. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Teacher Salary Data, 2014. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Beach Public Schools, 2014. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Preschool Initiative, 2015. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Association of Superintendents (VASS), 2014. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Quality Service Review (VSQR), 2014. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Virtual, 2014. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Virtual, 2014. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- IV. Special Projects and Studies: Secretariat, 2002-2010., Extent: 1.05 cubic feet (3 boxes). (Box 5-7;)
  - Budget, 2014-2016 (1 of 5). (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Budget, 2014-2016 (2 of 5). (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Budget, 2014-2016 (3 of 5). (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Budget, 2014-2016 (4 of 5). (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Budget, 2014-2016 (5 of 5). (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), 2015-2016. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Challenged Schools, 2015 (1 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Challenged Schools, 2015 (2 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Challenged Schools, 2015 (3 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Challenged Schools, 2015 (4 of 4). (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Classrooms Not Courtrooms, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Consolidation Study, 2015-2016. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Early Childhood Foundation, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Education Bills, 2014-2016. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Education Technology, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Executive Agreements. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Financial Aid, 2016. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Graduate Rate Update, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - High School Redesign, 2016. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Lumina Foundation, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - P-16, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Project Discovery, 2014-2015. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Round Table Notes, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) Budget, 2014-2016. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) Data, 2014-2016 (1 of 3). (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) Data, 2014-2016 (2 of 3). (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) Data, 2014-2016 (3 of 3). (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - School Readiness Committee, 2015. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL), 2015 (1 of 2). (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Standards of Learning (SOL), 2015 (2 of 2). (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Substance Use on Campus, 2015. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Virginia 529/SOAR, 2015. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Vaccines for Children (VFC) Annual Meeting, 2016. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Virginia School Boards Association (VSBA), 2014. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Workforce Development, 2015. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Youth Entrepreneurship, 2014. (Box 7, Folder 8)